Department of Astrophysics Radboud University Nijmegen, The Netherlands ✓ rtprincy@gmail.com

Tahina Princy Ranaivomanana

PhD Candidate

? rtprincy in rtprincy http://rtprincy.github.io

PROFILE

Fourth-year PhD candidate pursuing a dual degree at Radboud University (Netherlands) and KU Leuven (Belgium), specialising in multi-wavelength time-series data analysis and machine learning applications in stellar astrophysics. Skilled in Python programming and experienced with deep learning frameworks such as TensorFlow and PyTorch for data modeling, time-series characterisation, and classification. Published in peer-reviewed journals with extensive experience in international collaborations.

EXPERIENCE

PhD project Radboud University — KU Leuven

The Netherlands - Belgium

10/2021 - Present

- Conducted unsupervised machine learning analyses with t-SNE and UMAP on Gaia DR3 multi-band lightcurves to identify and characterise the variability of \sim 1,500 hot subdwarf stars.
- Designed and implemented frequency analysis tools for sparsely sampled multi-colour lightcurves from MeerLICHT observations, achieving significant advancements in periodicity search.

MPhil project 2020 - 2021University of Manchester United Kingdom

• Developed semi-supervised GAN models for pulsar data synthesis and classification, aligning with large radio surveys (SKA).

MSc project 2016 - 2017University of Antananarivo Madagascar

• Investigated the formation and evolution of young massive clusters in interacting galaxies using photometry and population synthesis code

Teaching Assistantship

Radboud University

•	Delivered tutorials for data analysis and astronomical instrumentation courses	2023 - 2024
•	 Delivered tutorials for a Data Analysis course 	2021

KU Leuven

• Supervised 2 bachelor research projects (two students per project) 2022

EDUCATION

Joint PhD candidate, Radboud University — KU Leuven	10/2021 — Present
MPhil in Astronomy, University of Manchester	2020 - 2021
M.Sc. in Astronomy, University of Antananarivo	2016 — 2017
B.Sc. Honours in Astrophysics, University of Antananarivo	2015 — 2016
B.Sc in Physics, University of Antananarivo	2012 — 2015

· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·	
SKILLS	
Programming	 Python: Conduct big data analysis with libraries such as Pandas, NumPy, SciPy, and Astropy SQL: Perform SQL query to retrieve datasets from astronomical databases Bash scripting: Automate task execution, job scheduling, and data pipeline management
Machine learning	 Familiar with Tensorflow, Keras, Pytorch libraries Perform classification, prediction, and clustering related tasks on tabular, time-series, and image data Deep learning: Perform synthetic data/image generation tasks for imbalanced learning
Astronomy software	 Topcat: TAP query, data manipulation, and visualisation MESA & GYRE: Perform basic modelling tasks Period04: Frequency search — pre-whitening tasks
Data handling	Experience with large actronomical databases: PlackCEM TTE TESS Caia

Data handling Experience with large astronomical databases: BlackGEM, ZTF, TESS, Gaia

RELEVANT PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATION

- [1] P. **Ranaivomanana**, M. Uzundag, C. Johnston, et al. "Variability of hot sub-luminous stars and binaries: Machine learning analysis of Gaia DR3 multi-epoch photometry". In: *arXiv e-prints*, arXiv:2411.18609 (Nov. 2024), arXiv:2411.18609. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2411.18609. arXiv:2411.18609 [astro-ph.SR].
- [2] P. Ranaivomanana, C. Johnston, P. J. Groot, et al. "Identifying and characterising the population of hot sub-luminous stars with multi-colour MeerLICHT data". In: 672, A69 (Apr. 2023), A69. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202245560. arXiv: 2302.07266 [astro-ph.SR].

CERTIFICATION

Teaching training course: Offered by Radboud University (Online certificate)

Oxoford machine learning school certificate (Online certificate)

Advanced Machine Learning and Signal Processing: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

Data Analysis with Python: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

Exploratory Data Analysis for Machine Learning: Offered by IBM Skills Network (online certificate)

PRIZES AND GRANTS

 Receipt of the Leids Kerkhoven-Bosscha Fonds (LKBF) grant (EUR 600) to attend the TASC/KASC 15 conference in P Receipt of the Leids Kerkhoven-Bosscha Fonds (LKBF) grant (EUR 500) to attend the Oxford machine learning scho Recipient of the UK's Newton Fund/DARA Big Data MPhil Bursary Receipt of SKA/SARAO grant to attend the 2nd Big Data Africa School — South Africa Selected as a trainee for the Development in Africa with Radio Astronomy (DARA) Basic Training Programme 	
Conferences Attended & Contributions	
BlackGEM meeting (talk) — Manchester, United Kingdom	2024
KOPAL 2024 conference (flash talk) — Litomysl, Czech Republic	2024
TASC/KASC 15 conference (Poster) — Porto, Portugal	2024
 Malagasy Astronomy Meeting (Talk) — Antananarivo, Madagascar 	2023
AMCVn5 workshop (<i>Poster</i>) — Armagh, UK	2023
• sdOB11 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Armagh, UK	2023
 MW-Gaia WG2 conference (Talk) — Sofia, Bulgaria 	2023
TASC/KASC13 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Leuven, Belgium	2022
sdOB10 conference (<i>Poster</i>) — Liege, Belgium	2022
EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES AND MEMBERSHIPS	
Help commissioning BlackGEM for two weeks in LaSilla, Chile	2023
• Student member of the Malagasy Astronomical Society (MAS) — IAU-adhering organisation for Madagascar 2	017 — Present
Student member of the African Astronomical Society (AfAS)	021 — Present
 Participated in African Space Generation Advisory Council (AF-SGAC) / DARA Big Data Hackathon 	2020
 Project leader of a OAD/DARA funded project: Madagascar Astronomy Magazine 	2018
 Member of the IAU100 National Committee: leader of national activities during the IAU100 celebration 	2019

2019

National Coordinator of Malagasy Astronomical Society (MAS) — IAU-adhering organisation for Madagascar